Hello friends, when a person
buys health insurance, he
buys it in two ways, first through the agent who
comes to his house, tells him the features of the product, tells him the
premium and if he
understands the product, then he buys it, on the
other hand, he buys it through the bank, when he
goes to the bank for some work, then the
bank employee tells him the product,
tells him the features and if he understands it, then he buys it,
but when the customer gets into a dilemma,
when the policy told in the bank and the
policy told by the agent is of the company,
but the premium of both is different, there the
policy told in the bank
looks cheap and the policy told by the agent
looks expensive and the person feels that the
agent has added his commission, that is why it is an
expensive policy and he buys the bank policy,
I tell you friends, both the
policies are different, so today in this video
we will tell you the difference between the two policies,
so my name is Abhishek, first of all let's
talk about bank health
insurance, friends,
health insurance is a group health
insurance in which the bankers make
a contract with the company and have a
minimum business commitment.  The
health insurance company makes a commitment to
provide standard features with the subscription, whereas
retail health insurance is an open
insurance which can be taken by every individual.
Now let's talk about who
can take this policy. Bank health insurance can be
taken only by the employees of the bank and its customers,
whereas on the other hand retail health
assured can be taken by every individual. Now let's talk about what
all things are covered in both the policies, right from
housebreaking expenses to road
ambulance, organ donor tax free and post
hospital expenses, all these things are covered
in both the policies. Now let's talk about
who pays the premium, in case of
bank health insurance the bank
pays the premium to the health insurance company
and in case of retail health insurance,
whoever is the policy holder pays the premium to the company. Next is the proposer, in case of bank
health
insurance the bank itself is the proposer of the policy,
whereas in retail health insurance
policy the policy holder is the proposer of the policy,
next is the insurance of the policy.
In retail health insurance you can
also get a subscription ranging from Rs 500000 to Rs 2 crore to Rs 3 crore.  You
get the option of Rs. 1000/-, whereas in bank health
insurance, you get limited options.
Next is rider coverage. In retail health
insurance, you get many rider
coverages like Kritika LS Rider,
Hospital Cash Benefit Rider, Personal
Accident Rider. However, in bank health
insurance, either there are no riders
or even if they are provided, they are limited.
Next is claim service. Friends,
here is the biggest difference between both the products.
If you have cashless treatment, then there will be
almost no problem in both the products. However,
if due to some reason you get
treatment in a non-network hospital, then in this case, retail
health insurance
provides you complete service where
they also fill out your form, your company
also maintains follow-up and tries to pay you till the end.
Whereas
in bank health insurance, you do
not get any personal service. If you have a claim, you have to
contact the bank employee. Many times,
even the bank employees do
not know the process and if they are relieved, they give you the call center
number or a particular
company number.  It gives
you the option to contact the head so that you can get the claim.
Next is the
portability service. Friends, in case of
retail health insurance, you
get the portability service in which you can port your
existing policy to another company.
If the
claim service or premium of your existing policy
is too high or you are
not satisfied with the services of the agent, then
you can port your policy. On the
other hand, there is no portability option in bank health insurance policies.
If the bank leaves the existing health insurance
company and leaves with another health insurance
company, then you have two options: either
you can continue with another health insurance company
or if
you want to continue with the existing health insurance company, then
you will have to
directly go to the health insurance company
and you will have to request to convert from group health
insurance to retail health insurance.
But the final decision is of the bank health insurance company whether it will convert
you from group to
retail or not. In case of
retail health insurance, if you do
not accept this claim, then the company will have to check your base submission
every year.  It increases the premium, which
goes up to a maximum of 100% or 200%, whereas bank health
insurance does
not offer such a service. Even if there is a discount, it is
limited. Now let's talk about the premium.
Compared to retail health insurance,
bank health insurance premiums are more
discounted because it is a standard product.
Bank health insurance is a
customized product. However, in
retail health insurance, if the company
increases the premium tomorrow,
you have the option of shifting to another company.
However, in bank health insurance,
you do not get such an option. If
tomorrow there are too many claims on a policy offered by the bank
and the health
insurance company increases its premium, the
bank also has to accept it.
If the bank accepts it, you will also have to
accept it. So, friends,
we have covered both types of health insurance. I
hope you liked the information.
Please comment in the comment section and
tell us which health insurance you
prefer: retail health insurance or
group health insurance. We
deal with all the major health insurance companies.
If you have any health insurance
concerns, please let us know below.  You
can contact on the given number, we will try to give you a like on the page.
If you have any
health insurance related query, you
can ask us in the comment box, we will
try to answer your questions. If you
like the video, then like, share and
subscribe. Thank you very much.